CHAPTER 4

Ambedkar’s Ideas of Nation and
Nation Building

From Sentimentality to Institutionalism

INTRODUCTION

In the preceding chapters, we have analysed the processes of reductionism and erasures associated with Ambedkar in various aspects of academia and creative fields. We are by now aware that mainstream media, academia, and intelligentsia have played a dominant and decisive role in reducing him only as a ‘Dalit Leader’. At the most, a few progressive intellectuals have called him ‘Chief Architect of the Indian Constitution’. Even in this address, many individuals were not comfortable, and that is why a high-profile journalist, who went on to become a Cabinet Minister of India, wrote a book-length volume to belittle Ambedkar’s contributions to the making of the Indian constitution and, thereby, in the process of nation building.

It is also a fact that barring a few (Ram 1995), universities, intellectuals, and scholars have not engaged with Ambedkar’s broad canvas of knowledge. His contributions in the spheres of understanding social categories of individual, caste, Hindu social order, problems of Indian women and Indian minorities, etc., have not been analysed in academia in detail. Above all, his ideas about nation and nation building have also been neglected in mainstream academia.

However, in the earlier chapter, we have already seen how the Dalit movement led by the Dalits themselves has provided Babasaheb Ambedkar visibility in contemporary times. Based on empirical data about the association of masses to a particular leader, the number of statues built by the individuals at their own expense, types of celebrations on his birth, conversion to Buddhism, and commemoration on his mahaparinibbana day, Ambedkar can be termed as the omnipresent organic leader of modern India. We have also observed how he has become famous and acceptable internationally.

The processes associated with Ambedkar’s colossal personality have forced the mainstream academia and intelligentsia, in contemporary times, to nominally include him in the curriculum syllabus of social sciences at the higher education and in the competitive exams like Union Public Service Commission or State Services Commissions. However, even today, there is no reflexivity on his thoughts in university classrooms, and questions in the exams, on Ambedkar are still asked only as optional so that teachers and students can easily avoid reading him. However, a few social scientists have argued that Ambedkar is intellectually head and shoulders above most of the Congress leaders because of his more serious training in the London School of Economics and the Columbia University, New York. Anderson (2012: 52) has also highlighted that Ambedkar was the only intellectual who had written serious academic and rational work on the partition of India.

It is in this context that this essay tries to understand the notion of ‘Nation’ and his pioneering contributions to the process of nation building. The essay will broadly deal with the following aspects related to his conceptualization of nation:

(a) Is India a nation?

(b) Why is India not a nation?

(c) What is a nation?

(d) How a Nation would be built?

(e) How to keep the unity and integrity of a Nation intact.

IS INDIA A NATION?

At the outset, Ambedkar, like many others, believed that India was not a nation but a nation in the making (Ambedkar 1994: 1217). He made this fact very clear as early as the 1930s during his conflict with Gandhi. According to Ambedkar, ‘The Anglo-Indians were never tired of proclaiming that India was not a nation’ (Ambedkar 1990(a): 29). It is true that the colonial administrators did not view the Indian subcontinent as one nation. Strachey (1888: 5) wrote, ‘. . . there is not and never was an India . . . no Indian nation, no people of India.’ In the same vein, Sheeley (1883: 255) commented, ‘India is . . . only a geographical expression like Europe or Africa. It does not make the territory of a nation and a language, but the territory of many nations and languages’ (Strachey (1888) and Sheeley (1883), as quoted in Oommen 2000: 1). Ambedkar also opined that even Dr. Rabindranath Tagore, the national poet of Bengal also agreed that India was not a nation (Ambedkar 1990(a): 29). That is why he emphasized that,

First of all there is no nation of Indians in the real sense of the word. The nation does not exist; it is to be created, and I think it will be admitted that the suppression of a distinct and separate community is not the method of creating a nation (Ambedkar 1991(c): 412).

Again, while speaking on 26 November 1949 when the Constituent Assembly was going to pass the constitution of independent India Ambedkar argued that,

I[in the past] politically-minded Indians resented the expression ‘the people of India’. They preferred the expression ‘the Indian nation’. I am of the opinion that in believing that we are a nation, we are cherishing a great delusion (Ambedkar 1994: 1217).

WHY IS INDIA NOT A NATION?

In this context, it will be worth mentioning the main reasons why Ambedkar refused to accept that India was not a nation. It would also be worth considering how he defined the nation and his scheme for building the nation.

RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN HINDUS AND
DALITS, HINDUS AND ABORIGINES

At the outset, Ambedkar wondered, ‘How can people divided into several thousands of castes be a nation?’ (Ambedkar 1994: 2017). Arguing at another place, Ambedkar highlighted the fact that castes were hurdles in the process of nation building. In his own words,

There is an utter lack among the Hindus of what the sociologists call ‘consciousness of kind’. There is no Hindu consciousness of any kind. In every Hindu, the consciousness that exists is the consciousness of his caste. That is the reason why the Hindus cannot be said to form a society or a nation (Ambedkar 1979: 50).

Ambedkar further went on to explain why castes are anti-national. In his words, ‘The castes are anti-national in the first place because they bring about separation in social life. They are anti-national also because they generate jealousy and antipathy between caste and caste’ (Ambedkar 1994: 1217). Not only that, Ambedkar also underlined that, ‘Caste is . . . the real explanation as to why Hindu has let the’ thirteen million aborigines amid civilization as savage without giving him medical aid to reform them and make them good citizens (Ambedkar 1979: 53). Therefore, he suggested that, ‘. . . we must overcome all these difficulties if we wish to become a nation in reality. For fraternity can be a fact only when there is a nation’ (Ambedkar 1994: 1216-17).

RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN HINDUS
AND MUSLIMS

If that was the case of the relationship between Hindus, Dalits, and Aborigines, Ambedkar further analysed whether ‘. . . there are enough affinities between Hindus and Muslims to constitute them into a nation. . .’ (Ambedkar 1990(a): 31). Ambedkar wondered,

Are there any common historical antecedents which Hindus and Muslims can be said to share together as a matter of pride or as matters of sorrow . . . so far, they have been just two-armed battalions warring against each other. There was no common cycle of participation for a common achievement. Their past is a past of mutual destruction—a past of mutual animosity, both in political as well as in religious fields (Ambedkar 1990(a): 35).

Ambedkar was clear that ‘while Hindus revere Prithviraj Chauhan, Rana Pratap, and Shivaji in history, the Muslims revere the likes of Mohammed Bin Qasim, Aurangzeb, etc.’ In the religious field, he argued, ‘. . . the Hindus draw their inspiration from the Ramayana, the Mahabharat, and Geeta. The Musalmans . . . derive their inspiration from Quran and Hadis’ (Ambedkar 1990: 36). Further, he reiterates, ‘In the absence of common historical antecedents, the . . . view that Hindus and Muslaman form one nation falls to the ground. To maintain it is to keep up a hallucination’ (Ambedkar 1990(a): 37).

RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN
HINDU PROVINCES

Along with analysing the nature of relationships between people belonging to various castes and communities, Ambedkar also analysed the relationship between various provinces and the Hindu majority. He says,

The Hindu provinces have no common traditions and no interest to bind them. It cannot be pretended that the Sikhs have any tenderness for the Bengalees or the Rajputs for the Madrasis. The Bengali loves only himself. The Madrasi is bound by his world. Maratha, who set out to destroy the Muslim empire in India, became a menace to the rest of the Hindus, whom they harassed and kept under their yoke for nearly a century. . . . On the other hand, the differences of language, race, and the conflicts of the past have been the most powerful forces tending to divide them (Ambedkar 1990(a): 12-13).

That is why Ambedkar concluded.

It is true that the Hindus are getting together, and the spirit moving them to become one united nation is working on them. But it must not be forgotten that they have not yet become a nation. They are in the process of becoming a nation (Ambedkar 1990(a): 13).

In the same vein, Ambedkar highlighted that

The Muslims have openly declared that they do not want to have any Central Government in India. . . . The Muslims feel that to accept one Central Government for the whole of India is consent to place the Muslims Provincial Government under a Hindu Central Government and to see the gain secured by the creation of Muslims Provinces by subjecting them to a Hindu Government (Ambedkar 1990(a): 12).

That is why, quoting Mohammad Iqbal’s position at the Round Table Conference Ambedkar opined that, ‘The Muslim way of escaping from the tyranny of Hindu Centre is to have no Central Government in India at all (ibid.: 12).

WHAT IS A NATION?

The logical question then is—If, according to Ambedkar, India is not a nation, then—What is a nation according to him? Before we answer that, we would like to engage ourselves with the idea of nation in general. Pecora (2001) has commented that ‘. . . while the nation may be a human invention, one that has played an enormous historical role in the last two centuries, it remains a piece of human history that has resisted firm definitions’. Therefore, it can be stated here that there is not a unified and final definition of ‘nation’. However, taking the help of Patterson, we can define a Nation as,

a people, a folk, held together by some or all of such more or less immutable characteristics as common descent, territory, history, language, religion, way of life, or other attributes that members of a group have from birth onward (Patterson 1975: 181).

On the other hand, Jaffrelot (2002: 7) uses Marcel Mauss’s definition of the nation to define it

. . . as forming a nation a society materially and morally integrated with a stable, permanent centralized political power, well-established borders, a relative moral and cultural unity of its inhabitants who consciously adhere to the state and its laws.

The significant aspect of this definition according to Jaffrelot is, ‘This definition rules out the presence of any intermediary bodies, be they linguistic groups or religious communities’. However, in the same vein, Jaffrelot extensively quotes Ernest Gellner to refute Marcel Mauss’s notion of ‘nation’. According to him,

The primordialist has been strongly criticized by Ernest Gellner, for whom ‘Men do not become nationalists from sentiments or sentimentality, atavistic or not, well-based or myth founded: They become Nationalist through genuine, objective, practical necessity, however obscurely recognized.’ In his theory of nationalism, Gellner assumes that there is always an unequal distribution of economic resources across the territory of a state. People ‘B’, originating from a deprived region, ask for its share, but another group, ‘A’, which is relatively more prosperous, resists this demand to retain the monopoly of its privileged situation. Therefore, it exercises discrimination toward ‘B’ put forward as a pretext for its racial or cultural inferiority. Then the member of group ‘B’ is bound to revolt and’ . . . their discontent can find ‘national’ expression: the privileged are manifestly different from themselves, even if the shared ‘nationality’ of the under-privileged men from B starts off from a purely negative trait, i.e., shared exclusion from privilege and from the ‘nation’ of the privileged. For Gellner, it is in these situations that ‘culture, pigmentation, etc., become important: Provide means of exclusion for the benefit of the published off identification, etc., for the under-privileged [. . .] Nationalism is not the awakening of nations to self-consciousness: It invents nations where they do not exist—but it does need some pre-existing differentiating marks to work on, even if, as indicated, they are purely negative (Jaffrelot 2002: 10).

However, it is interesting to note that sociologists like T.K. Oommen (2000: 1-18) argue that ‘Indian Nationalism’ was conceptualized under British colonialism and acquired broadly seven shades. These were: Nation as an ancient civilization, as composite culture, as a political entity, as a religious entity, as a geographical and religious entity, as a collection of linguistic entities, and as the unity of the little and great nation. To add further, the first three conceptualizations existed during the pre-Partition period. The fourth existed during the struggle for independence and continues still. The last three conceptualizations were the projects that emerged after Independence. Oommen says,

All available facts and experiences suggest that the two most critical elements in Nation formation are territory and language. These could be ancestral or adopted. Thus, if a people have a common homeland and adopt a common language, they could become a nation. Such an effort was made and is being pursued in India (Oommen 2000: 8).

SENTIMENTALITY AND AMBEDKAR’S
NOTION OF NATION

Taking a leaf, Ambedkar rejected race, language, and country as a basis for constituting a nation. He argued, ‘As a matter of historical experience, neither race nor language nor country has sufficed to mold people into a nation’ (Ambedkar 1990(a): 34). Quoting Renan, he argued,

that race must not be confused with nation . . . . The truth is there is no pure race. . . . Racial facts, important as they are in the beginning, have a constant tendency to lose their importance. Human history is essentially different from zoology. Race is not everything, as it is in the sense of rodents and felines (ibid: 34).

As for language,

Language invites reunion; it does not force it. The United States, England, Spanish America, and Spain speak the same language and do not form a single nation. On the contrary, Switzerland, which owes her stability to the fact she was founded by the assent of her sever counts three or four languages. In man, there is something superior to language-will. The will of Switzerland to be united despite the variety of her language is a much more important fact than a similarity of language, often obtained by persecution (ibid: 34).

As to a common country, Ambedkar quoted Renan,

It is no more the land than the race that makes a nation. The land provides a substratum, the field of battle and work; man provides the soul; man is everything in forming that sacred thing called a people. Nothing of a material nature suffices for it (ibid: 34).

Having shown that race, language, and country do not suffice to create a nation, Ambedkar quoted Renan to point out what is more necessary to constitute a nation. According to Renan:

A nation is a living soul, a spiritual principle. Two things, which in truth are but one, constitute the soul, this spiritual principle. One is in the past, the other in the present. One is the common possession of a rich heritage of memories; the other is the actual consent, the desire to live together, the will to preserve worthily the undivided inheritance that has been handed down. . . . The nation, like the individual, is the outcome of a long past of efforts, sacrifices, and devotion. . . . A heroic past, great men, and glory—form the social capital upon which a national idea may be founded. To have common glories in the past, a common will in the present: to have done great things together, to will to do the like again,—such are the essential conditions for the making of a people (Renan quoted in Ambedkar 1990(a): 35).

Furthermore, Renan argues that:

In the past, an inheritance of glory and regrets to be shared; in the future, alike ideal to be realized; to have suffered, rejoiced, and hoped together; all these things are worth more than custom houses in common and frontiers in accordance with strategical ideas; all these can be understood despite diversities of race and language . . . suffering in common is a greater bond of union than joy. Regarding national memories, mournings are worth more than triumphs; they impose duties and demand common effort (Renan, quoted in Ambedkar 1990(a): 35).

Such are the characteristics of the nation, according to Ambedkar, which is identical to the definition of Mauss, as discussed above, which is without any markers of religion, race, language, or territory but instead based on sentiments or will.

DIFFERENCE BETWEEN NATIONALITY
AND NATIONALISM

Apart from giving the characteristics of a nation, Ambedkar went on to differentiate between nationality and nationalism. Accordingly,

. . . there is a difference between nationality and nationalism. They are two different psychological states of the human mind. Nationality means ‘Consciousness of Kind’ awareness of the existence of that tie of Kinship (Ambedkar 1990(a): 39).

Further, he has explained that

Nationality is a social sentiment. It is feelings of a corporate sentiment of oneness that make those who are charged with it feel that they are kith and kin. This national feeling is a double-edged feeling. It is at once a feeling of fellowship for one’s own kith and kin and an anti-feeling for those who are not one’s own kith and kin. It is a feeling . . . which, on the one hand, binds together those who have it, so strongly that it overrides all differences arising out of economic conflict or social gradation and, on the other, severs them from those who are not of their kind. It is a longing not to belong to any other group. This is the essence of what is called a nationality and national feeling (Ambedkar 1990(a): 31).

On the other hand, Ambedkar elucidated that ‘Nationalism means ‘the desire for a separate national existence for those who are bound by this tie of kinship . . . there cannot be nationalism without the feeling of nationality being in existence’ (Ambedkar 1990(a): 39). It is here that Ambedkar highlighted the relationship between Nationality and Nationalism as well. According to him, although nationalism cannot exist without nationality,

. . . the converse is not always true. The feeling of nationality may be present, and yet the feeling of nationalism may be quite absent. . . . For nationality to flame into nationalism, two conditions must exist. First, there must arise the will to live as a nation. Nationalism is a dynamic expression of that desire. Secondly, there must be a territory which nationalism could occupy and make it a state and cultural home of the nation (Ibid.: 39).

AMBEDKAR’S SCHEME OF NATION BUILDING:
A SHIFT TOWARDS INSTITUTIONALISM

If we analyse the idea of the Indian nation in the light of the characteristics of the nation as discussed above, two things become amply clear. On the one hand, there is an utter lack of national feeling between Dalits, Other Backward Castes, Aborigines, and the so-called upper-caste Hindus. On the other hand, there is no common antecedent between Muslims and Hindus. Third, Indian women were also subjugated and were excluded from social, political, and economic institutions because of caste and patriarchy. In this way, we can conclude from the aforesaid analysis that Ambedkar identified a lack of nationality hence a lack of fraternity within the aforesaid groups. Probably, it is here Ambedkar is moving away from the notion of the nation based on sentimentality to the notion of nation as given by Gellner, who has argued that people become because of genuine, objective, practical necessity, ‘nation’ may emerge from ‘shared exclusion’ and ‘culture, pigmentation, etc.’ which provides means of identification for the under-privileged class (Gellner, quoted in Jaffrelot 2002: 10).

Jaffrelot (2002) has used this aforesaid theory to prove the separatism of Muslims in British India, the crystallization of Bengali nationalism in Pakistan, and the assertion of Sindhis in Pakistan. Hence, if we must integrate these separatist tendencies emerging out of ‘genuine objective and practical necessity’ and ‘shared exclusion’ then we need to provide people with those necessary conditions that can subside their separatist assertion for an independent state. We have discussed the case of Hindu women here separately however they should be considered as a subsection of Hindu society only. In the light above the writer of this article is of the view that one must take the following steps for nation building.

FOUR CHARACTERISTICS OF NATION BUILDING

REALIZATION INDIA IS NOT A NATION

The first step in Ambedkar’s scheme of nation building is the realization of the fact that India was not a nation. In his words,

The sooner we realize that we are not as yet a nation in the social and psychological sense of the word, the better for us. For then only we shall realize the necessity of becoming a nation and seriously think of ways and means of realizing the goal (Ambedkar 1994: 2017).

FORGETFULNESS

The second step in the process of nation building will be forgetting the turbulent and warring past. In this context, taking a clue from Renan, Ambedkar emphasized the importance of forgetfulness as a factor in the creation of a nation that can be observed in France, where the union of Northern and Southern France took place despite a century of conflict. But today, no one has forgotten it, and they both have become one nation. Therefore, Renan concluded that ‘the essence of the nation is that all its individuals should have things in common; and also, that all of them should hold many things in oblivion’ (Renan quoted in Ambedkar 1990(a): 37). Perhaps, Ambedkar was using this fact for both so-called upper caste Hindus and Dalits on the one hand, and for Hindus and Muslims, on the other. Although a very difficult proposition, Ambedkar proposed expecting that all the sections of the Indian society would forget their past of animosity and hatred to make a positive beginning.

FREEDOM OF SERVILE CLASSES IS ALSO A REALITY

The third aspect of Ambedkar’s scheme of nation building was that all the subjugated collectivities should be granted their legitimate rights so that they should be free from subjugation. In his own words,

Philosophically it may be possible to consider a nation as a unit, but sociologically it cannot but be regarded as consisting of many classes and the freedom of the nation if it is to be a reality must vouchsafe that the freedom of the different classes comprised in it, particularly those who are treated as servile classes (Ambedkar 1991(c): 201-2).

BREAKING THE MONOPOLY OF THE
GOVERNING ELITE

The fourth characteristic of Ambedkar’s scheme of nation building was dismantling the privileges of the governing elite and breaking their monopoly on ‘political power’. He cautioned the Constituent Assembly about the dangers of a tiny group of people monopolizing power. He had opined,

Political power in this country has too long been the monopoly of a few. This monopoly has not merely deprived them of their chance of betterment; it has sapped them of what may be called the significance of life. These downtrodden classes are tired of being governed. They are impatient to govern themselves (Ambedkar 1994: 1218).

Ambedkar was trying to draw a parallel between the ruling elites of French and Japanese society, and their role in the process of nation building after the revolution in their respective countries with the ruling elite of Indian society. In Ambedkar’s words,

It would be instructive to compare the attitude of the governing class in India with the attitude taken by the governing class in other countries in times of crisis. . . . In France, when the Revolution broke out and demanded equality, the governing class in France [Clergy and Nobles] voluntarily came forward to give up its powers and its privileges and to merge itself into the mass of the nation. . . . It was impossible. . . . Yet a good part of them agreed to the demands of the commons and gave France a constitution based upon liberty, equality, and fraternity (Ambedkar 1991(c): 225).

The attitude of the governing classes in Japan during the period between 1855 and 1870—a period in which Japanese people were transformed from a feudal society into a modern nation was even more patriotic than the attitude of the governing classes in France . . . there were four classes in Japanese Society (1) The Daimyos, (2) The Samurai, (3) The Hemin or the common folk and (4) The Eta or the outcastes standing one above the other in order of graded inequality. . . . The Daimyos and the Samurai realized that it was impossible to transform this feudal society, with its class composition and class rights, into a modern nation with equality of citizenship. Accordingly, the Daimyos, charged with the spirit of nationalism and anxious not to stand in their way of national unity, came forward to surrender their privileges and to emerge themselves in the common mass of people (Ambedkar. 1991(c): 225-6).

The governing class in India has no such intention of making any sacrifice on the altar of Indian freedom. Instead of surrendering its privileges in the name of nationalism, the governing class in India is using or misusing the slogan of nationalism to maintain its privileges. Whenever the servile classes ask for reservations in the legislatures, in the Executive, and public services, the governing class raises the cry of nationalism in danger. People are told . . . all questions regarding reservations . . . are inimical to national unity and therefore . . . a sin to stand out for such reservation and create dissension. . . . The governing class in India does not merely refuse to surrender its power and authority; it never loses an opportunity to pour ridicule on the political demands of the servile classes (Ambedkar 1991(c): 226).

Under these circumstances, along with the ‘representative government’ for all Indians, Ambedkar wanted four different collectivities that were excluded or denied their legitimate rights to be included directly in the institutions of governance and thereby into the mainstream of Indian society so that the nation could evolve. In other words, the said collectivities should be granted their legitimate rights, which were it was due to them. Though it is a fact that Ambedkar had raised a host of other issues that were significant in the process of nation building, here we are restricting ourselves to his struggle to establish the rights and representation of the following four collectivises. The four collectivises that come to mind and which form part of Ambedkar’s core ideas of nation and nation building include:

REPRESENTATIVE GOVERNMENT
FOR ALL INDIANS

Dalits (ex-Untouchables)

Backward Castes/Classes

Muslims and other minorities

Women, in general, and Hindu women, in particular.

A REPRESENTATIVE GOVERNMENT
FOR INDIANS

Ambedkar explained that the British denied Indians representative government on the pretext of division in the population on the lines of caste and creed. However, Ambedkar contested this argument by giving a counterargument that if Indian society is not fit for representative government because it is divided on caste and creed, then how can American Society be fit for representative government? The American population is divided not only politically but also based on scientific, industrial, and religious aims and attitudes. Moreover, the US population is also divided based on language, religion, moral codes, and traditions. Finally, Ambedkar also highlighted that American society too has a different population of Poles, Dutch, Swedes, Germans, Russians, etc. Despite aforesaid divisions, if American society was fit to have a representative government, then why not India (Ambedkar 1979: 248)?

Second, Ambedkar went on to show that the division of Indian society is qualitatively different than the division existing in American society. He highlighted the fact that, unlike American Society, the Indian population is divided because they do not have common aims, beliefs, aspirations, knowledge, common understanding, or what sociologists call like-mindedness to form a community (Ambedkar 1979: 248-9). According to him, to be like-minded with others is to be in communication with them and to participate in their activity. In this way, each group may create its own distinctive type of like-mindedness.

But where there are more groups than one to be brought into a political union, there would be conflict among different like-mindedness. So long as the group remains isolated, the conflict is bound to continue and prevent the harmony of action. It is the isolation of the groups that is the chief evil in India. The evil ceases to exist where there is endosmosis because it allows people to re-socialize their attitude. In place of the old, it creates a new like-mindedness, which is the representatives of the interests, aims, and aspirations of all the groups concerned. Hence, he concluded that ‘Like-mindedness is essential for a harmonious life, social or political, and this depends upon the extent of communication, participation, or in a word, endosmosis’ (Ambedkar 1979: 49). Hence, Ambedkar emphasized the legitimate and functional need of representative government with the self-representation of various groups comprised in it for nation building.

DALITS AND THEIR RIGHTS AS A CITIZEN

At the outset, Ambedkar wanted to establish the rights of those people who did not have rights as citizens. Ambedkar quoted Jefferson, to whom ‘. . . politics was the only affair of policing by the State so that the rights of people were maintained without disturbance. . . . The question is, what is there for the State to police if there are no rights?’ That is why Ambedkar wanted to establish the rights of the Dalits, as they were not treated as citizens. Ambedkar also argued,

The untouchables are usually regarded as objects of pity but ignored in any political scheme on the score they have no interest to protect. And yet, their interests are the greatest. Not that they have large property to protect from confiscation. But they have their very persona confiscated. The socio-religious disabilities have dehumanized the untouchables, and their interests at stake are, therefore, the interests of humanity. The interests of property are nothing before such primary interests. . . . The untouchable is not even a citizen. Citizenship is a bundle of rights such as (1) personal liberty, (2) personal security, (3) right to hold private property, (4) equality before law, (5) liberty of conscience, (6) freedom of opinion and speech, (7) right to assembly, (8) right of representation in a country’s Government and (9) right to hold office under the State (Ambedkar 1979: 255-6).

So, it is clear from the above that Ambedkar wanted to establish the rights of the Dalits at the outset so they did not feel excluded. Probably, he believed if the rights of the Dalits were established, they would not raise their voices for separate ‘Achutistan’ (Separate land for Achuts or Untouchable) (Kumar 2002 and Juergesnmeyer 1982).

DALITS AND THE QUESTION OF
THEIR SELF-REPRESENTATION

Ambedkar did not raise the problems related to the aforesaid categories in one go. Rather, he took their problem as and when the country faced a crisis regarding these groups. But certainly started his public life by highlighting the problems and issues of the Dalits (the ex-untouchables). Ambedkar wanted self-representation of the Dalits in the government, cabinet, bureaucracy, etc. Explaining its importance, Ambedkar argued in his written statement given to the Southborough Committee on the franchise in 1919 that

As the government is the most important field for the exercise of individual capacities, it is in the interest of the people that no person as such should be denied the opportunity of actively participating in the process of government. That is to say, popular government is not only government for the people but by the people. To express the same in a different way, the representation of opinions by itself is not sufficient to constitute popular government. To cover its true meaning it requires personal representation as well. It is because the former is often found without the latter that the Franchise Committee must see in devising the franchise and constituencies for a popular government in India, it provides for both, i.e., representation of opinions and representation of persons (Ambedkar 1979: 247).

INCLUSION OF DALITS, BACKWARDS,
AND MUSLIMS IN THE INSTITUTIONS
OF GOVERNANCE

Ambedkar not only asked for self-representation for every citizen of the country, but he also advocated for self-representation via reserved nominations for Dalits (the ex-untouchables), Backward Classes to whom he referred as non-Brahmins and Muslims. Why was the self-representation of Dalits, Backward Classes, and Muslims necessary? Ambedkar answered this question in a written representation submitted to the Simon Commission, also known as the Indian Statutory Commission, in the year 1928. To begin with, in his representation, Ambedkar expressed his concern over the domination of Brahmin and other allied castes in the public services of British bureaucracy in India (Ambedkar 1982: 394).

Ambedkar argued that when the ‘Dalits, Mohammedans, and non-Brahmins ask for their representation, the Brahmins and the allied castes argue that the appointment should be done through competition’. Ambedkar questioned the very basis of appointment through competition. He declared the aforesaid process as unfair. Why was it unfair? It was so because

Those circumstances presuppose that the educational system of the state is sufficiently democratic and is such that facilities for education are sufficiently widespread and sufficiently used to permit all classes from which good public servants are likely to be forthcoming to compete. Otherwise, even with the system of open competition, large classes are sure to be left out in the cold. This basic condition is conspicuous by its absence in India so that to invite Backward Classes to rely upon the results of competitive examinations as a means of entry into the public services is to practice delusion upon them (Ambedkar 1982: 395).

Therefore, this was the second reason for supporting the self-representation of Dalits and non-Brahmins, and Muslims in administrative institutions.

Discussing the administrative basis for reservation, he argued, ‘Those who lay exclusive stress upon efficiency as the basis for recruitment to the administration appears to be nothing more than the process of applying the law as enacted by the legislative’ (ibid.). However, according to Ambedkar,

Administration in modern times involves far more than the scrutiny of status for the sake of knowing the regulations of the state. Often under the pressure of time or for convenience, a government department is nowadays entrusted with wide power of rulemaking (ibid.).

Further, he argued that

It must be accepted as beyond dispute that such wide powers of rule-making affecting the welfare of large classes of people cannot be safely left into the hands of the administrators drawn from a particular class which as a matter of fact is opposed to the rest of the population in its motives and interests, does not sympathize with the living forces operating in them, is not charged with their wants, pains, cravings and desires and is inimical to their aspirations, simply because it comes out best by the test of education (ibid.).

Therefore, Ambedkar preferred giving self-representation through nomination.

MORAL REASON FOR
REPRESENTATION OF DALITS

According to Ambedkar, the third reason for self-representation, specifically for Dalits, was moral. This can be extended to backward classes and minorities as well. Highlighting the moral evils arising out of the exclusion of a person from the public service, Ambedkar quoted Gopal Krishna Gokhale. Gokhale had raised the same issue of exclusion of so-called upper caste Indians from British bureaucracy. Emphasizing the exclusion of Indians from public services, he opined that,

A kind of dwarfing or stunting of the Indians is going on under the present system. We must live all days of our lives in an atmosphere of inferiority and the tallest of us must bend so that the exigencies of the existing system may be satisfied. The upward impulse . . . is denied to us. The full height to which our manhood is capable of rising can never be reached by us under the present system. The moral elevation that every self-governing people feel cannot be felt by us. Our administrative and military talent must gradually disappear, owing to sheer disuse, till at last our lot, as hewers of wood and drawers of water in our own country is stereotyped (quoted in Ambedkar(1982: 397).

Drawing an analogy between the Brahmins and allied castes with the foreign agency, i.e., the British, Ambedkar (Ambedkar 1982: 395-6) argued:

Is it not open to the backward classes to allege against Brahmins and allied castes all that was alleged by the late Mr Gokhale on behalf of Indian people against the foreign agency? Is it no open to the Depressed Classes, the non-Brahmins, and the Mohammedans to say that by their exclusion from the Public Service, a kind of dwarfing or stunting of their communities is going on? Can they not complain that as a result of their exclusion, they are obliged to live all the days of their lives in an atmosphere of inferiority, and the tallest of them has to bend in order that the exigencies of the existing system may be satisfied? Can they not assert that upward impulses which every schoolboy of a Brahmanical community feels that he may one day be a Sinha, a Sastri, a Ranade, a Pranjpe, and which may draw forth from him the best efforts of which he is capable are denied to them? Can they not indignantly assert that the full height to which their manhood is capable of rising can never be reached by them under the present system? Can they not lament that the moral elevation that every self-governing person feels cannot be felt by them and that their administrative talents must disappear owing to sheer disgust till at last their lot as hewers of wood and drawers of water in their own country is stereotyped? The answer to these queries cannot but be in the affirmative. If to exclude the advanced communities from entering into the public service of the country was a moral wrong, the exclusion of the backward communities from the same field must be a moral wrong and if it is a moral wrong it must be righted.

For the inclusion of Dalits and other marginal sections in the public services, Ambedkar also highlighted that the demand for the Indianization of public services did not rest on consideration of efficient administration; rather, it was condemned as it was found to be wanting in those qualities that make for human administration. It is, therefore, he pointed out that those who clamoured for the Indianization of public services are themselves opposed to the inclusion of the Depressed and Backward Classes (Ambedkar 1982: 395-6). That is why he proposed that

A certain number of vacancies in Superior Services, Class I, and Class II, and also in the Subordinate Services should every year be filled by a system of nomination with pass examination. . . . Such nomination shall be reserved to the Depressed Classes, the Mohammedans and the Non-Brahmins in order of preference herein indicated until their numbers in the services reach a certain proportion (Ambedkar 1982: 398).

This was possibly the first time that anyone had made a demand for the representation of Dalits in the public services, though Ambedkar had already made a demand for their political representation as early as 1919. It is a fact that the, then, Indian National Congress did nothing worth mentioning for the self-representation of the Dalits during this period and even after the formation of its government in 1937. The major development of the period is attributed to Ambedkar serving as a member of the Viceroys’ Executive Council. It was he who issued an office order in 1943 to reserve 8.33 per cent of places in the Central Government Services for the Dalits. In fact, this order, which reserved the posts for the Dalits, had replaced an earlier general order for general preference for the Dalits in their recruitment in the Services (Ambedkar 1990(a): 475).

NECESSITY OF SELF-REPRESENTATION

Why at all self-representation was necessary? According to Ambedkar, this was necessary because the aims, beliefs, aspirations, and knowledge of the caste Hindus and the Dalits differ. That means they do not have like-mindedness. In his own words, ‘Between two Hindus, caste-like mindedness is more powerful than the like-mindedness due to their both being Hindus’ (ibid.: 249). Therefore, he emphasized that there would be a conflict of interest between the Hindus and the Dalits and, hence, caste Hindus could never represent the interests and opinions of Dalits if the latter did not get self-representation.

Ambedkar wanted self-representation for the Dalits because he was also convinced that only the Dalits could voice these interests. In his own words, as can be easily seen, they can be represented by the untouchables alone. They are distinctively their own interests, and none can truly voice them. . . . Untouchability constitutes a definite set of interests which the untouchables alone can speak for (ibid.: 256).

Second, the personal representation for the Dalits is also important because

A government for the people, but not by the people, is sure to educate some into masters and others into subjects. . . . To be specific, it is not enough to be electors only. It is necessary to be law-makers; otherwise, who can be law-makers will be masters of those who can only be electors (ibid: 251).

That is why Ambedkar demanded not only a separate electorate for Dalits but also reservation in the cabinet as well. According to him,

Just as it is necessary that the Depressed Classes should have the power to influence governmental action by seats in the Legislature, so it is also desirable that the Depressed Classes should have the opportunity to frame the general policy of the government. This they can do only if they can find a seat in the cabinet. The Depressed Classes, therefore, claim that in common with other minorities, their rights to be represented in the Cabinet should be recognized. With this purpose in view, the Depressed Classes propose that in the Instrument of Instructions, an obligation shall be placed upon the Governor and the Governor-General to endeavour to secure the representation of the Depressed Classes in the Cabinet (Ambedkar 1991(c): 51-2).

GANDHI’S OPPOSITION TO DALITS’
SELF-REPRESENTATION

Gandhi opposed the representation of the Dalits by special constituencies. He emphasized that the special representation of the untouchables (Dalits) ‘Will create a division in the Hinduism which I (Gandhi) cannot possibly look forward to with any satisfaction whatsoever’ (Ambedkar 1991(c): 69). In fact, Gandhi was ready to accept the conversion of the Dalits to any other religion but was not ready to grant representation based exclusively on their votes though the same existed for the other minorities. In the words of Gandhi,

I do not mind Untouchables, if they so desire, being converted to Islam or Christianity. I should tolerate that, but I cannot possibly tolerate what is in store for Hinduism if there are two divisions set forth in the villages. Those who speak of the political right of Untouchables do not know their India, do not know how Indian Society is today constructed, and therefore I want to say with all the emphasis that I can command that if I were the only person to resist this thing, I would resist with my life (as quoted in Ambedkar 1991(c): 69).

INCLUSION OF MUSLIMS IN
THE CONSTITUENT ASSEMBLY

Along with the representation of Dalits and backward castes in the structures of the state, Ambedkar was a strong votary of the inclusion of Muslims in the Constituent Assembly. His position came to the fore when he vehemently pleaded for their inclusion despite the Muslim League’s announcement of their desire for a separate state. Ambedkar emphasized non-violent methods for the inclusion of Muslims in the Constituent Assembly. While speaking in the Constituent Assembly, which met for the first time on 9 December 1946, to move a resolution for making the Indian constitution, he, along with other members of the Constituent Assembly, argued that it would not be proper for the Assembly to proceed to deal with the resolution of framing the constitution of free India, while Muslim League was absent. He pointed out a particular para of the resolution that could prevent the Muslim League from entering the Constituent Assembly (Ambedkar 1994: 9-10).

Ambedkar was aware of the diversity and deep divide existing between Hindus and Muslims. Yet, he believed that every group should be included in the process of making decisions about the nation. In the constituent assembly, he explained

. . . Our difficulty is not about the ultimate future. Our difficulty is how to make the heterogeneous mass that we have today take a decision in common and march on the way, which leads us to unity. Our difficulty is not with regard to the ultimate; our difficulty is with regard to beginning . . . therefore, I should have thought that in order to make us willing friends, in order to induce every party, every section in this country to take on the road, it would be an act of greatest statesmanship for the majority party even to make a concession to the prejudices of people who are not prepared to march together and it is for that, that I propose to make this appeal. . . . Let us even make a concession to the prejudices of our opponents, bring them in, so that they may willingly join us on marching upon that road, which, as I said, if we walk long enough, must necessarily lead us to unity (Ambedkar 1994: 10).

To include the Muslim League in the process of the constitution, Ambedkar went on to argue,

. . . I want all of us to realize that whether we are right or wrong, whether the position that we take is in consonance with our legal rights. . . . This is too big a question to be treated as a matter of legal rights. It is not a legal question at all. We should leave aside all legal considerations and make some attempts where those who are not prepared to come will come. Let us make it possible for them to come (Ambedkar 1994).

Ambedkar was very much charged with the feelings of dignity and destiny of the nation that he advised the members of constituent assembly

. . . that another attempt may be made to bring about a solution of the dispute between the Congress and the Muslim League.

This subject is so vital, so important that I am sure it could never be decided on the mere basis of the dignity of one party or the dignity of another party (Ambedkar 1994: 12).

That is why he explained that

When deciding the destinies of nations, dignities of people, dignities of leaders and dignities of parties ought to the for nothing. The destiny of the country ought to count for everything (Ibid.).

Regarding Congress and Muslim League impasse Ambedkar was very much disturbed. He was very clear that the Congress and Muslim League problem should be solved as soon as possible. For which he played down the violence. He spoke, in the Constituent Assembly, with anguish,

. . . I do not know what plans the Congress party . . . has in its mind? . . . it seems to me there are only three ways by which the future will be decided. Either there shall have to be surrender by the one party to the wishes of the other. . . . The other way would be . . . negotiated peace, and the third way would be open war . . . certain members of the Constituent Assembly . . . are prepared to go to war (Ibid.: 13).

Refuting the option of war, Ambedkar (ibid.) expressed his anguish by emphasizing the point that:

I must confess that I am appalled at the idea that anybody in this country should think of solving the political problems of this country by the method of war. I do not know how many people in this country support that idea. A good many perhaps do, and the reason why . . . they do is because most of them . . . believe that the war . . . would be a war on the British. . . . But I have no hesitation . . . to place before this house . . . if that war comes in this country . . . it will not be a war on the British. It will be a war on the Muslims. It will be a war on the Muslims or which is probably worse; it will be a war on a combination of the British and the Muslims.

In this conflict between Congress and the Muslim League, to bring down the temper of the house, Ambedkar quoted from Burke, who had rejected the idea of violence applied by the British in conquering the colonies of the United States and bringing them under their subjection arguing that ‘. . . the use of force is but temporary. It may subdue for a moment, but it does not remove the necessity of subduing again; and a nation is not governed which is perpetually to be conquered’ (ibid.). Ambedkar further quoted Burke to highlight the fact of the uncertainty of terror in overpowering a nation. In the words of Burke,

. . . Terror is not always the effect of force and an armament is not a victory. If you do not succeed, you are without resources for conciliation; failing, force remains; but, force failing, no further hope of reconciliation is left. Power and authority are sometimes brought by kindness, but they can never be begged as alms by an impoverished and defeated violence (Ibid.: 13-14).

The third objection to force was ‘. . . that you impair the object by your very endeavours to preserve it. The thing you fought for is not the thing which you recover; but depreciated, sunk, wasted, and consumed in the contest’ (ibid.: 14). Therefore, Ambedkar concluded,

If there is anybody who has in his mind the project of solving the Hindu-Muslim problem by force, which is another name of solving it by war, in order that the Muslims may be subjugated and made to surrender to the Constitution that might be prepared without their consent, this country would be involved in perpetually conquering them. The conquest would not be once and forever (Ibid.).

And suggested that the assembly should exercise the sovereign powers with wisdom because that is the only way by which we can carry every section of the country together, and that is the way to achieve unity (Ibid.).

REFERENDUM AGAINST ABRUPT PARTITION

Ambedkar, for the unity of the nation, instead of an abrupt partition of the country, mooted that ‘The issue of Pakistan being one of self-determination must be decided by wishes of the people’ (Ambedkar 1994: 392). The structure he proposed was the referendum of Muslims and non-Muslims and the limitation of districts with Muslim majority and non-Muslim majority areas (ibid.: 393). He argued that Muslims may stop with the delimitation of the boundaries of Pakistan or, if dissatisfied, may ask for a separate state (ibid). Muslims may also agree to live under a common central government, say, for a period of ten years, and put the Hindus on trial. Hindus will have an opportunity to show that the minorities can trust them. The Muslims will learn from their experience how far their fears of the Hindu Raj are justified.

Ambedkar further explained that

There is another possibility also that the Musalmans of Pakistan having decided to separate forthwith may after a period become so disgusted with Pakistan that they might desire to come back and be incorporated into the Hindustan, and be one people subject to one single constitution (Ibid.: 393).

Last but not least, Ambedkar commented optimistically, ‘I personally prefer . . . a separation for ten years and union thereafter’ (ibid.). He preferred this because, in his opinion,

It would be much better that the Musalmans should have the experience of Pakistan Union after an experience of Pakistan would be stable and lasting. . . . The scheme takes account of the fact that the Hindu sentiment is against. . . . It also recognizes the fact that the Muslim demand for Pakistan may only be a passing mood (Ibid.: 394).

Despite the division and animosity between Congress and the Muslim League, Ambedkar (1994: 9) was convinced about the unity and development of the nation. He told the Assembly optimistically

. . . I have got not the slightest doubt in my mind as to the future evolution and the ultimate shape of the social, political, and economic structure of this country. I know today, we are divided politically, socially, and economically. We are a group of warring camps, and I may go even to the extent of confessing that I am probably one of the leaders of such a camp. But, Sir, with all this, I am quite convinced that given time and circumstances, nothing in the world will prevent this country from becoming one. With all our castes and creeds, I have not the slightest hesitation that we shall, in some form, be a united people. I have no hesitation in saying that notwithstanding the agitation of the Muslim League for the partition of India, someday enough light would dawn upon the Muslims themselves, and they too will begin to think that a United India is better even for them.

Such was the optimism and commitment of Ambedkar when it came to the issue of nation building.

ESTABLISHING RIGHTS OF HINDU WOMEN

Apart from securing the rights of the Dalits, Other Backward castes, and Muslims in the processes of nation building, Ambedkar, as the first Law Minster of independent India, also introduced a Bill to safeguard the rights of Hindu women. However, one should keep in mind that it was not all of a sudden that Ambedkar made this effort for women’s rights. Rather it was his long-time conviction to which he was giving a practical shape. For instance, Ambedkar had long back, in 1942, in the Scheduled Caste Federation’s Women Conference, emphasized that ‘I measure the progress of the community by the degree of progress of women of that community have made’. Further, Ambedkar had also analysed the wretched condition of Indian women in Indian history through his influential articles like ‘Manu’s Madness’; ‘The Change from Paternity to Maternity’ (1987(b)) and ‘The Woman and the Counter-Revolution’ 1987(a). That is why he was instrumental in introducing certain bills for establishing the rights of women—like equal pay irrespective of sex (1991(d): 143), The Mines Maternity Benefit Act 1941 (ibid.: 264-6), and prohibiting employment of women underground in coal mines in 1946 (Ibid.: 958).

Together with the aforementioned efforts for analysing the status of Indian women and establishing rights for them, when he became the first law minister of independent India, Ambedkar introduced the bill, which envisaged securing dignified and equal status for Hindu women. It is interesting to note that there were rights of inheritance and maintenance in the Bill. There were laws against dowry. Instead of polygamy, Ambedkar introduced monogamy as the sanctioned way of marriage. The Hindu marriage became a contract instead of a sacrament. The consent of the wife was to be made compulsory in the event of the adoption of the child by the couple.

Ambedkar envisioned empowering Hindu women through all these rights and thereby building a strong nation. The Hindu Code Bill introduced in the parliament gives insight into what and how Ambedkar had thought about empowering Hindu women. He had mooted that

In the order of succession to a deceased Hindu, the Bill seeks to make four changes. One change is that the widow, the daughter, and the widow of a pre-deceased son are all given the same rank as the son in the matter of inheritance. In addition to that, the daughter is also given a share in her father’s property (Ambedkar 1995: 6).

Ambedkar, in his proposed Hindu Code Bill, attempted ‘Consolidate the different categories of stridhana into one single category of property and lay down the uniform rule of succession’ (ibid.: 7). In the same vein, he opposed dowry and was conscious of the treatment meted out to girls because of dowry. Therefore, while moving the Bill in the parliament, he opined,

All the members of the House know . . . how girls who bring an enormous lot of property . . . by way of dowry or Stridhan or gift are treated . . . with utter contempt, tyranny, and oppression (Ibid.: 8).

Therefore, Ambedkar mooted that,

property which is given as dowry . . . shall be treated as a trust property, the use of which will ensure to woman and . . . neither her husband nor the relations of her husband will have any interest in that property (Ibid.).

The provision of separate maintenance for the woman who lives away from her husband was also made by Ambedkar. The Bill recognized that there are circumstances where the wife has lived away from her husband, and she can claim separate maintenance from the husband. The following are conditions in which a wife can claim maintenance from her husband:

(1) suffering from a loathsome disease; (2) if a husband keeps a concubine; (3) if a husband is guilty of cruelty; (4) if a husband has abandoned her for two years; (5) if he has converted to another religion (Ibid.: 8-9).

As far as the Hindu marriage is concerned, he introduced the idea of civil marriage. He opined that the code would dispense with case and sub-caste in the event of civil marriage. He argued, ‘Marriage under this Bill be valid irrespective of the caste or sub-caste of the parties entering into marriage’ (ibid.: 9). Furthermore, Ambedkar abolished polygamy, which was permissible under the existing Hindu Law. He argued, ‘Under the new law, it is monogamy which is prescribed’ (ibid.: 10). Ambedkar also introduced the provision to dismantle the sacramental status of the Hindu marriage in which it cannot be dissolved. He made it a contract by introducing the provision of divorce. Ambedkar introduced seven grounds of divorce:

(1) desertion; (2) conversion to another religion; (3) keeping concubine or becoming a concubine; (4) incurably unsound mind; (5) a virulent and incurable form of leprosy; (6) venereal diseases in a communicable form; (7) cruelty (Ibid.: 10).

Addressing the question of adoption, ‘under the code’, he made the consent of the women necessary for the husband (Ibid.).

In this manner, Ambedkar envisaged to empower the Hindu women. It is pertinent to note here that the Indian parliament did not pass different clauses of the Hindu Code Bill tabled by Ambedkar, and he had to resign from the Nehru cabinet as the first Law Minster of independent India (ibid.: 1317-27). This is testimony to the fact of how much Ambedkar was committed to the cause of Indian women. It is heartening to note that, subsequently, most of the clauses proposed by Ambedkar in the Hindu Code were passed one-by-one by the Indian parliament.

FUTURE OF THE INDIAN NATION

Ambedkar not only explained the existing nature of the Indian society, defined the notion of a nation, why India is not a nation, and gave the scheme of national building, but he also gave five principles for keeping the Indian nation safe in the future. Ambedkar was aware of the Indian history of how the nation was colonized several times, and that is why he was concerned for the future of the nation. Following are the five principles for safeguarding the future of the Indian nation and society:

Self-introspection by the Indians.

Adherence to constitutional means.

Denunciation of hero worship.

Establishment of social and economic democracy, along with political democracy.

Changing government by the people to government for the people.

SELF-INTROSPECTION AND THE
FUTURE OF THE NATION

The first and foremost principle suggested by Ambedkar to guard the future of the Indian nation is ‘self-introspection’ by the Indians. On the last day of the Constituent Assembly, 26 November 1949 when the Constitution of India was to be finally handed over to the President of India, he told the Constituent Assembly to have self-introspection. Ambedkar (1994: 1213-14) argued,

. . . my mind is so full of the future of our country. . . . On 26 January 1950, India will be an independent country (Cheers). What would happen to her independence? Will she maintain her independence, or will she lose it again?. . . . It is not that India was never an independent country. The point is that she once lost the independence she had. Will she lose it a second time? It is this thought which makes me most anxious for the future. What perturbs me greatly is the fact that not only did India once lose her independence, but she lost it by the infidelity and treachery of some of our own people. In the invasion of Sind by Mahommed-bin-Kasim, the military commanders of King Dhar accepted bribes from the agents of Mahommed-bin-Kasim and refused to fight on the side of their King. It was Jaichand who invited Mahommed Ghori to invade India and fight against Prithvi Raj and promised him the help of himself and the Solanki kings. When Shivaji was fighting for the liberation of Hindus, the other Maratha noblemen and Rajput Kings were fighting the battle on the side of Mogul Emperors. When the British were trying to destroy the Sikh Rulers, Gulab Singh, their principal commander, sat silent and did not help to save the Sikh kingdom. In 1857, when a large part of India declared a war of independence against the British, the Sikhs stood and watched the event as silent spectators.

Besides reminding the assembly of the drawbacks India had suffered in the historical past, Ambedkar highlighted the dangers of new enemies like new political parties with diverse and opposing political interests. Ambedkar (1994: 1215) cautioned the Assembly,

Will history repeat itself? . . . Will Indians place the country above their creed, or will they place the creed above the country? I do not know. But this much is certain if the parties place creed above country, our independence will be put in jeopardy a second time and probably be lost forever. This we must all resolutely guard against. We must be determined to defend our independence with the last drop of our blood. . . . What would happen to her democratic constitution? Will she be able to maintain it, or will she lose it again. . . . It is not that India did not know what democracy is. There was a time when India was studded with republics, and even where there were monarchies, they were either elected or limited. They were not absolute. It is not that India did not know parliaments or parliamentary procedure. A study of the Buddhist Bhikkhu Sangha discloses that not only were there parliaments, the Sangha were nothing but parliaments. The Sangha knew and observed all the rules of parliamentary Procedures known to modern times. . . . This democratic system India lost. Will she lose it a second time? I do not know, but it is quite possible in a country like India, where democracy from its long disuse must be regarded as something quite new—there is the danger of democracy giving place to dictatorship. It is quite possible for this newborn democracy to retain its form but give place to dictatorship becoming much greater.

ADHERENCE TO CONSTITUTIONAL MEANS

Further, Ambedkar’s vision for keeping the future of Indian democracy intact included adherence to constitutional means as well. He emphasized,

If we wish to maintain democracy not merely in form, but also in fact, what we must do? The first thing . . . we must do is to hold fast to constitutional methods of achieving our social and economic objectives. It means we must abandon the bloody methods of revolution. It means that we must abandon the method of civil disobedience, non-cooperation, and satyagraha. When there was no way left for constitutional methods to achieve economic and social objectives, there was a great deal of justification for unconstitutional methods. But where constitutional methods are open, there can be no justification for these unconstitutional methods. These methods are nothing but anarchy and the sooner they are abandoned, the better for us (Ambedkar 1994: 1215).

DENUNCIATION OF HERO WORSHIP

Similarly, Ambedkar saw a threat to the future of democracy and, thereby, the nation because of hero worship. That is why he emphasized that

we must . . . observe the caution which John Stuart Mill has given to all who are interested in the maintenance of democracy, namely, not ‘to lay their liberties at the feet of even a great man, or to trust him with powers which enable him to subvert their institutions (Ibid.: 1215).

Further, Ambedkar specifically warned against hero-worship (bhakti) in politics and also in journalism. According to him:

There is nothing wrong with being grateful to great men who have rendered life-long services to the country. But there are limits to gratefulness. As has been well said by the Irish Patriot Daniel O’Connell, ‘No man can be grateful at the cost of his honour, no woman can be grateful at the cost of her chastity, and no nation can be grateful at the cost of its liberty’. This caution is far more necessary in the case of India than in the case of any other country, for in India, bhakti, or what may be called the path of devotion or hero-worship, plays a part in its politics unequaled in magnitude by the part it plays in the politics of any other country in the world. Bhakti in religion may be the road to the salvation of the soul. But in politics, bhakti or hero-worship is a sure road to degradation and to eventual dictatorship (Ibid.: 1215).

As far as Indian journalism is concerned, Ambedkar had emphasized long back.

Journalism in India was once a profession. It now has become trade. . . . To accept a hero and worship has become its principal duty. . . . It is written by drum boys to glorify their heroes. Never has the interest of the country been sacrificed so senselessly for the propagation of hero-worship. Never has hero-worship become so blind as we see in India today (Ambedkar 1979: 227).

That is why Ambedkar suggested the first or foremost duty of Indian Journalism should be to,

Regard itself as the responsible advisor of the public. To give the news uncolored by any motive, to present a certain view of public policy which it believes to be for the good of the community, to correct and chastise without fear all those, no matter how high, who have chosen a wrong or a barren path (Ibid.: 227).

In this context, while criticizing both Gandhi and Jinnah, Ambedkar had also highlighted the biases of Congress Press. In this regard, he suggested that countrymen should understand,

. . . that the country is greater than the men, that the worship Mr Gandhi or Mr Jinnah, and service to India are two very different things and may even be contradictory to each other (Ibid.: 209).

DEMOCRACY SOCIAL, ECONOMIC,
AND POLITICAL

For strengthening the Indian nation and democracy, Ambedkar believed that we should not only be content with the establishment of political democracy, but rather we should stretch it to social and economic as well. Therefore, he emphasized that

We must . . . not . . . be content with mere political democracy. We must make our political democracy a social democracy as well. Political democracy cannot last unless there lies at the base of its social democracy (Ambedkar 1994: 1216).

Ambedkar went on to define social democracy as

. . . a way of life which recognizes liberty, equality, and fraternity as the principles of life. These principles of liberty, equality, and fraternity are not to be treated as separate items of a trinity (Ibid.).

In this context, Ambedkar’s explanation of the nature of this trinity can be considered another decisive contribution. According to him,

They form a union of trinity in the sense that to divorce one from the other is to defeat the very purpose of democracy. Liberty cannot be divorced from equality; equality cannot be divorced from liberty. Nor can liberty and equality be divorced from fraternity. Without equality, liberty would produce the supremacy of the few over many. Equality without liberty would kill individual initiative. Without fraternity, liberty and equality could not become a natural course of things. . . . We must begin by acknowledging the fact that there is a complete absence of two things in Indian society. One of these is equality. On the social plane, we have in India a society based on the principle of graded inequality which means elevation of some and degradation of others. On the economic plane, we have a society in which there are some who have immense wealth as against many who live in abject poverty (Ibid.).

Therefore, Ambedkar stated that,

On the 26 January 1950, we are going to enter into a life of contradictions. In politics we will have equality and in social economic life we will have inequality. In Politics, we will be recognizing the principle of one man one vote, and one vote one value. In our social and economic life, we shall, by reason of our social and economic structure, continue to live this life of contradiction. How long shall we continue to live this life of contradictions? If we continue to deny it for long, we will do so only by putting our political democracy in peril. We must remove this contradiction at the earliest possible moment or else those who suffer from inequality will blow up the structure of political democracy (Ambedkar 1994: 1216-17).

Ambedkar, for establishing social democracy, emphasized the following:

The second thing we want is recognition of the principle of fraternity. What does fraternity mean? Fraternity means a sense of common brotherhood of Indians—if Indians are one people. It is the principle that gives unity and solidarity to social life. . . . The realization of this goal is going to be very difficult. . . . In India there are castes. The castes are anti-national . . . because they bring about separation in social life . . . also . . . generate jealousy and antipathy. . . . But we must overcome all these difficulties if we wish to become a nation in reality. For fraternity can be a fact only when there is a nation (Ibid.).

About the above discussion on equality, liberty, and fraternity, it will be worth mentioning the source from which he borrowed these principles of democracy. He argues that he has not borrowed them from the French Revolution; rather, he has borrowed them from Buddhism. In his own words,

Every man should have a philosophy of life, for everyone must have a standard by which to measure his conduct. And philosophy is nothing but a standard by which to measure. . . . Positively, my philosophy. May be said to be enshrined in three words: Equality, Liberty, and Fraternity. Let no one, however, say that I have borrowed my philosophy from the French Revolution. I have not. My philosophy has roots in religion and not in political science. I have derived them from my Master, the Buddha. In his philosophy, liberty and equality had a place; but he added that unlimited Liberty destroyed equality and absolute equality left no room for liberty. In his philosophy, Law had a place only as a safeguard against the breaches of Liberty and Equality; but he did not believe that law can be a guarantee for breaches of Liberty and Equality. He gave the highest place to the fraternity as the only real safeguard against the denial of liberty or equality or fraternity, which was another name for brotherhood or humanity, which was again another name for religion (Ambedkar 2003: 503).

FROM GOVERNMENT BY THE PEOPLE TO
GOVERNMENT FOR THE PEOPLE

Last but not least, to keep the future of our nation safe, the political elite should strive to change the nature of the government from ‘Government by the people’ to ‘Government for the people’. It was important to do so because Ambedkar thought that political power in this country had too long been the monopoly of the few. This monopolization of politics by a minority has deprived the downtrodden of the chances of their betterment; it has also sapped them of the significance of their lives (Ambedkar 1994: 2017-18). Therefore, he emphasized,

These downtrodden classes are tired of being governed. They are impatient to govern themselves. This urge for self-realization in the downtrodden classes must not be allowed into a class struggle or class war. It would lead to a division of the House. That would be a day of disaster. For, as has been well said by Abraham Lincoln, a house divided against itself cannot stand very long. Therefore, the sooner the room is made for the realization of their aspiration, the better for the few, the better for the country, the better for the maintenance of its independence, and the better for the continuance of its democratic structure. This can only be done by the establishment of equality and fraternity in all spheres of life.

Ambedkar cautioned that after Independence it has thrown great responsibility on citizens of the country. We have to meet the aspirations of the people:

People are fast changing. People . . . are being moved by new ideologies. They are getting tired of the government by the people. They are prepared to have a Government for the people. . . . If we wish to preserve the Constitution in which we have sought to enshrine in principle of Government of the people, for the people, and by the people, let us resolve not to be tardy in the recognition of the evils that lie across our path and which induce people to prefer Government for the people to Government by the people, nor to be weak in our initiative to remove them. That is the only way to serve the country (Ambedkar 1994: 1218).

CONCLUSION

In the light of the detailed aforementioned discussion and explanation, we can argue safely that Ambedkar was the only leader of his times who tried to argue, based on empirical facts, that India is not a nation rather a nation in the making. Based on empirical reality, Ambedkar also tried to explain why India was not a nation. Third, he defined what exactly he means by a nation. Fourth, he presented an alternative process of nation building.

We have also observed in the discussion that Ambedkar adhered to the notion of the nation based on both sentiments and also based on objective conditions of deprivation. Therefore, he differentiated between nationality and nationalism. He also underlined the fact that without the nation, there will not be fraternity, and in the absence of fraternity, equality, and liberty will not be the reality. He held that fraternity, equality, and liberty are interconnected and interdependent. However, he treated fraternity on a higher pedestal than equality and liberty.

Further, apart from making people realize that India is not a nation Ambedkar tried to make people realize that there can be five very significant ways through which we can build a nation. These were—forgetfulness, freedom of the servile classes, breaking the monopoly of the governing classes and allowing self-representation to the excluded groups. Besides, Ambedkar also pleaded that a nation cannot be built without establishing the rights of various sections of society that comprised it, especially the rights of the erstwhile servile classes. In this regard, he pleaded for the self-representation of ex-untouchables (Dalits), Other Backward Castes, Tribals, religious minorities and women. In this sense we can accept a nation as an idea of emancipation for the people suffering double disadvantage one that of a colonialism and two that of a caste ridden hierarchical society.

Along with the analysis of the notion of nation as propounded by Ambedkar, this chapter has also discussed five principles to keep the future of our nation safe as have been discussed by Ambedkar in his thoughts. These five principles are self-introspection by the Indians, adherence to constitutional means, denunciation of hero worship in politics, the establishment of social and economic democracy along with political democracy, and last, but not least, changing government by people to government for the people. In this way, we have engaged with Ambedkar’s idea of nation and nation building. By doing so, we have engaged with another aspect of his knowledge production and have tried to deconstruct the process of reduction of his persona, life, and mission to a leader belonging to a particular identity.

REFERENCES

Anderson, Perry, 2012, The Indian Ideology, Three Essays Collective, Haryana.

Ambedkar, B.R., 1979, ‘On Constitutional Reforms: Evidence before the Southborough Committee’, in Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 1, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra Mumbai.

——, 1982, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 2, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1987(a), ‘Manu’s Madness in Riddles of Hinduism’, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 4, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai (pp. 215-25).

——, 1987(b), ‘The Change from Paternity to Maternity in Riddles of Hinduism’, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 4, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai (pp. 226-32).

——, 1987(c), ‘The Woman and the Counter-Revolution’ in Dr.

Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 3, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai (pp. 429-40).

——, 1989, ‘The Indian Ghetto: The Centre of Untouchability’, in Dr Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 5, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1990(a), ‘A Nation Calling for Home’ in Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 8. Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1991(c), ‘What Congress and Gandhi have done to the Untouchables?’ in Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 9, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai, Mumbai.

——, 1991(d), ‘The Mines Maternity Benefit (Amendment) Bill’ in Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 10, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai, Mumbai, pp. 264-6.

——, 1994, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 13, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1995, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 14 (Part One), Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 2003, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 17 (Part Three), Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

Jaffrelot, Christophe (ed.), 2002, Pakistan: Nationalism without a Nation, Manohar, New Delhi.

Juergensmeyer, Mark, 1982, Religion as Social Vision: The Movement against Untouchability in 20th Century Punjab, University of California Press, Berkley, USA.

Kumar, Vivek, 2010, ‘Ambedkar’s Idea of Nation and Nation Building’, Journal of Human Rights Global Focus, International Human Foundation, Delhi (pp. 69-85).

Oommen, T.K., 2000, ‘Conceptualizing Nation and Nationality in South Asia’, in S.L. Sharma and T.K. Oommen (eds.) Nation and National Identity in South Asia, Orient Longman, New Delhi.

Patterson, W., 1987, ‘On the Subnations of Western Europe’, in Nathan Glazer (eds.), Ethnicity Theory and Experience, Harvard University Press, Cambridge.

Pecora, P. Vincent (ed.), 2001, Nations and Identities, Blackwell Publishers, Massachusetts, USA.

Ram, Nandu, 1995, Beyond Ambedkar: Essays on Dalits in India, Har-Anand Publications, New Delhi.